The first time I cried underwater
كان أول بكاء لى تحت الماء
was in 2008,
عام 2008،
the island of Curaçao,
فى جزيرة كوراساو
way down in the southern Caribbean.
جنوب منطقة البحر الكاريبي.
It's beautiful there.
المكان جميل هناك.
I was studying these corals for my PhD,
كنت أدرس تلك الشعاب المرجانية لشهادتى في الدكتوراه،
and after days and days of diving on the same reef,
و بعد أيام و أيام من الغوص على نفس الشعاب
I had gotten to know them as individuals.
كنت قد تعرفت عليهم كأفراد.
I had made friends with coral colonies --
ولقد قمت بعقد صداقات مع المستعمرات المرجانية --
totally a normal thing to do.
وهو شئ طبيعى تماماً القيام به.
Then, Hurricane Omar smashed them apart and ripped off their skin,
وبعد ذلك، حطمهم "إعصار عمر" وجردهم من جلودهم
leaving little bits of wounded tissue that would have a hard time healing,
تاركاً القليل من الأنسجه المجروجة والتى سيكون لها وقتاً عصيباً للشفاء،
and big patches of dead skeleton that would get overgrown by algae.
وبقع كبيرة من الهياكل العظمية الميتة والتى تنمو بإفراط بواسطة الطحالب
When I saw this damage for the first time,
عندما رأيت هذا الضرر لأول مرة؛
stretching all the way down the reef,
تمددتُ علي طول الطريق أسفل الشعاب
I sunk onto the sand in my scuba gear
وغَرقت في الرمل في معدات الغوص،
and I cried.
وبكيت.
If a coral could die that fast,
إذا كان المرجان يمكن أن يموت بهذه بسرعة،
how could a reef ever survive?
فكيف يمكن للشعاب أن تنجوا؟
And why was I making it my job to try to fight for them?
ولماذا جعلتها وظيفتى لمحاولة القتال من أجلهم؟
I never heard another scientist tell that kind of story
فلم أسمع عالِم آخر يسرد قصة من هذا القبيل
until last year.
حتي العام الماضي.
A scientist in Guam wrote,
كتب عالم في غوام،
"I cried right into my mask,"
"بكيت في قناعي"
seeing the damage on the reefs.
عند رؤية الضرر على الشعاب المرجانية.
Then a scientist in Australia wrote,
ثم كتب عالم في أستراليا،
"I showed my students the results of our coral surveys,
'لقد أظهرت لطلابي نتائج استطلاعاتنا المرجانية
and we wept."
وبكينا'.
Crying about corals is having a moment, guys.
إن البكاء علي المرجان يحظي بلحظة شاعرية يا رفاق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's because reefs in the Pacific
وهذا لأن الشعاب في المحيط الهادئ
are losing corals faster than we've ever seen before.
يفقدون المرجان أسرع مما قد رأينا من قبل.
Because of climate change,
بسبب تغير المُناخ؛
the water is so hot for so long in the summers,
فالماء حار جدا لفترة طويلة في الصيف،
that these animals can't function normally.
وأن هذه المخلوقات لا تستطيع العمل بشكل طبيعي.
They're spitting out the colored algae that lives in their skin,
وإنهم يبصقون الطحالب الملونة التي تعيش في جلودهم
and the clear bleached tissue that's left usually starves to death
وعادة تموت الأنسجة المبيضة جوعاً؛
and then rots away.
ثم تتعفن.
Then the skeletons are overgrown by algae.
ثم تنمو الهياكل العظمية بإفراط بواسطة الطحالب.
This is happening over an unbelievable scale.
وهذا يحدث علي نطاق لا يصدق.
The Northern Great Barrier Reef lost two-thirds of its corals last year
ولقد فَقد الحاجز المرجاني الشمالي العظيم ثلثي المرجان في العام الماضي
over a distance of hundreds of miles,
من مسافات تبلغ مئات الأميال.
then bleached again this year,
ثم ابيضت مرة أخري هذا العام
and the bleaching stretched further south.
وإمتد التنييض للجنوب.
Reefs in the Pacific are in a nosedive right now,
وفي المحيط الهادئ تأخذ الشعاب في الهبوط حالياً
and no one knows how bad it's going to get,
ولا أحد يعرف كم سيكون سيئاً،
except ...
ما عدا ...
over in the Caribbean where I work,
في منطقة البحر الكاريبي حيث أعمل،
we've already been through the nosedive.
ولقد مررنا بالهبوط بالفعل.
Reefs there have suffered through centuries of intense human abuse.
وقد عانت الشعاب خلال قرون من الإعتداءات الانسانيه القاسية.
We kind of already know how the story goes.
نحن نعرف بالفعل كيف تبدو القصة.
And we might be able to help predict what happens next.
وقد نكون قادرين علي التنبؤ بما سيحدث بعد ذلك.
Let's consult a graph.
دعونا نراجع الرسم البيانى.
Since the invention of scuba,
فمنذ إختراع التنفس تحت الماء،
scientists have measured the amount of coral on the seafloor,
قاس العلماء كمية المرجان في قاع البحر
and how it's changed through time.
وكيفية تغيرها مع مرور الوقت.
And after centuries of ratcheting human pressure,
وبعد قرون من الجهد البشري،
Caribbean reefs met one of three fates.
فقد إجتمعت الشعاب الكاريبية بواحد من ثلاثه مصائر.
Some reefs lost their corals very quickly.
ففقدت بعض الشعاب مرجانيتها بسرعة كبيرة.
Some reefs lost their corals more slowly,
والبعض قد فقد مرجانيتها ببطء أكثر،
but kind of ended up in the same place.
ولكن نوعاً ما قد انتهي به الأمر في نفس المكان.
OK, so far this is not going very well.
حسنا، وحتى الآن هذا لا يسير علي ما يرام.
But some reefs in the Caribbean --
ولكن بعض الشعاب في منطقة البحر الكاريبي--
the ones best protected
وهي أفضل واحدة تمت حمايتها
and the ones a little further from humans --
وهي الأبعد قليلاً عن البشر --
they managed to hold onto their corals.
وتمكنوا من التمسك بشعابهم المرجانية.
Give us a challenge.
أعطنا التحدي.
And, we almost never saw a reef hit zero.
ونحن تقريباً لم نري أن الشعاب قد بلغت الصفر؟
The second time I cried underwater
وكانت المرة الثانية لبكائي تحت الماء
was on the north shore of Curaçao, 2011.
عام 2011 على الشاطئ الشمالي لكوراساو.
It was the calmest day of the year,
كان اليوم الأكثر هدوءاً من السنة،
but it's always pretty sketchy diving there.
ولكن دائماً ما يكون الغطس جميلٌ هناك.
My boyfriend and I swam against the waves.
ولقد سبحت أنا وصديقي ضد الأمواج.
I watched my compass so we could find our way back out,
وراقبت بوصلتى حتي نتمكن من العثور علي طريقنا للوراء
and he watched for sharks,
وراقب هو أسماك القرش،
and after 20 minutes of swimming that felt like an hour,
وبعد عشرون دقيقة من السباحة كادت تبدو وكأنها ساعة،
we finally dropped down to the reef,
ولقد هبطنا أخيراً للشعاب،
and I was so shocked,
و لقد صُدمت بشدة،
and I was so happy
وفرحت بشدة
that my eyes filled with tears.
وامتلأت عيناي بالدموع.
There were corals 1,000 years old lined up one after another.
فكان هناك مرجان يبلغ ألف عام يصطف واحداُ تلو الآخر.
They had survived the entire history of European colonialism in the Caribbean,
وقد نجوا من تاريخ الإستعمار الأوروبي بأكمله في منطقه البحر الكاريبي،
and for centuries before that.
ولقرون قبل ذلك.
I never knew what a coral could do when it was given a chance to thrive.
لم أكن أعرف ما يمكن للمرجان فعله عندما أُعطى فرصة للأزدهار.
The truth is that even as we lose so many corals,
والحقيقة هي أنه حتي ونحن نفقد العديد من المرجان،
even as we go through this massive coral die-off,
وتموت حتي ونحن نمضي خلال هذا المرجان الضخم
some reefs will survive.
وستنجوا بعض الشعاب.
Some will be ragged on the edge,
وسيكون البعض ممزقاً علي الحافة
some will be beautiful.
وسيكون البعض جميلاً.
And by protecting shorelines and giving us food to eat
وبحماية الشواطئ وإعطاءنا الطعام للأكل
and supporting tourism,
ودعم السياحة؛
they will still be worth billions and billions of dollars a year.
فإن قيمتها ستظل مليارات ومليارات الدولارات سنوياً.
The best time to protect a reef was 50 years ago,
وكان أفضل وقت لحماية الشعاب المرجانية قبل خمسون عاماً،
but the second-best time is right now.
ولكن الوقت الأفضل هو الآن.
Even as we go through bleaching events,
حتي ونحن نمضي من خلال أحداث التبييض
more frequent and in more places,
الأكثر تكراراً وفي أماكن أكثر،
some corals will be able to recover.
وستتمكن بعض الشعب المرجانية من التعافي.
We had a bleaching event in 2010 in the Caribbean
وفي عام 2010 كان لدينا ظاهرة إبيضاض في منطقة البحر الكاريبي
that took off big patches of skin on boulder corals like these.
والتي أقلعت بقعات كبيرة من الجلد علي المرجان الصخري مثل هؤلاء
This coral lost half of its skin.
ولقد فقد هذا المرجان نصف جلودهم.
But if you look at the side of this coral a few years later,
ولكن إذا نظرت إلي جانب هذا المرجان بعد سنوات قليلة
this coral is actually healthy again.
يعود هذا المرجان صحياً مرة أخري.
It's doing what a healthy coral does.
ويفعل ما يفعله المرجان الصحي.
It's making copies of its polyps,
فإنها تصدر نسخاً من بوليباتها المرجانية
it's fighting back the algae
وتعود إلي مقاتلة الطحالب
and it's reclaiming its territory.
وإستعادة أراضيها.
If a few polyps survive,
فإن نجى قلة من البوليبات
a coral can regrow;
فيمكن للمرجان أن ينمو؛
it just needs time and protection and a reasonable temperature.
إنها فقط تحتاج إلي الوقت والحماية ودرجة حرارة معقولة.
Some corals can regrow in 10 years --
فبعض المرجان يمكنه النمو في عشرة أعوام
others take a lot longer.
والبعض الآخر يستغرق وقتاً أطول.
But the more stresses we take off them locally --
ومن الضغوط الأكثر هي أن نأخذ منها محلياً --
things like overfishing, sewage pollution, fertilizer pollution,
أشياء مثل الصيد الجائر وتلوث مياة الصرف الصحى وتلوث الأسمدة
dredging, coastal construction --
والتجريف والبناء الساحلي --
the better they can hang on as we stabilize the climate,
ومن الأفضل أن يتشبثوا مثلنا في تحقيق إستقرار المناخ،
and the faster they can regrow.
واستطاعتهم في النمو أسرع.
And as we go through the long, tough and necessary process
وكما نمر بعمليات طويلة وصعبة وضرورية
of stabilizing the climate of planet Earth,
لتحقيق إستقرار المناخ لكوكب الأرض،
some new corals will still be born.
ولا تزال بعض الشعاب المرجانية تُولد.
This is what I study in my research.
وهذا ما أدرسه في بحثي.
We try to understand how corals make babies,
ونحاول أن نفهم كيف للشعاب أن تنجب صغاراً
and how those babies find their way to the reef,
وكيف يمكن لهؤلاء الصغار إيجاد طريقهم إلي المرجان
and we invent new methods to help them survive
ونبتكر أساليب جديدة لمساعدتهم علي البقاء
those early, fragile life stages.
في تلك المراحل المبكرة.
One of my favorite coral babies of all time
إن واحداً من صغار المرجان المفضل لدي في كل الأوقات
showed up right after Hurricane Omar.
ظهر مباشرة عقب "إعصار عمر".
It's the same species I was studying before the storm,
إنه نفس النوع الذي كنت أدرسه قبل العاصفة،
but you almost never see babies of this species --
ولكنك تقريباً لم ترى صغار من هذا النوع -
it's really rare.
فإنه نادر جداً.
This is actually an endangered species.
في الحقيقة هذه هي الأنواع المهددة بالإنقراض.
In this photo, this little baby coral, this little circle of polyps,
وفي هذه الصورة يوجد طفل مرجاني صغير في هذه الدائرة الصغيرة من البوليبات،
is a few years old.
عمره بضع سنوات.
Like its cousins that bleach,
تبيض مثل أبناء عمومته
it's fighting back the algae.
وإنها تُعاود قتالِها للطحالب.
And like its cousins on the north shore,
ومثل أبناء عمومته علي الشاطئ الشمالى
it's aiming to live for 1,000 years.
إنها تهدف للعيش لألف عاماً.
What's happening in the world and in the ocean
ماذا يحدث في العالم والمحيط؟
has changed our time horizon.
فقد غيرت أفقنا الزمني.
We can be incredibly pessimistic on the short term,
يمكننا ان نكون متشائمين بشكل لا يصدق علي المدى القصير
and mourn what we lost
وحداداُ علي ما فقدنا
and what we really took for granted.
وما اتخذناه حقاً أمراً مفروغاً منه.
But we can still be optimistic on the long term,
ولكن لا يزال بإمكاننا أن نكون متفائلين علي المدى الطويل
and we can still be ambitious about what we fight for
ولا يزال بإمكتننا أن نكون طموحين حول ما نقاتل من أجله
and what we expect from our governments,
وما نتوقعه من حكومتنا
from our planet.
من كوكبنا.
Corals have been living on planet Earth for hundreds of millions of years.
تعيش الشعاب المرجانية علي كوكب الأرض منذ مئات الملايين من الأعوام.
They survived the extinction of the dinosaurs.
وإنهم نجوا من إنقراض الديناصورات.
They're badasses.
إنهم عُجاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
An individual coral can go through tremendous trauma and fully recover
فيمكن للمرجان الواحد أن يمر بصدمة هائلة ويتعافى تماماً
if it's given a chance and it's given protection.
لو اُتيحت لها الفرصة وأُعطي الحماية.
Corals have always been playing the long game,
ودائماً ما تلعب الشعاب المرجانية اللُعبة الطويلة المدي،
and now so are we.
والآن نحن كذلك.
Thanks very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)